Well, good morning, Canvas.
Thanks so much for joining us this morning, whether you're here at the Alamo, you're watching
online.
My name is Ryan.
I had the privilege of being one of the pastors here at Canvas.
I walked in this morning, and I was getting a hard time from some of our people for not
dressing up for Halloween.
And I told them I dressed up like a real pastor, because if you've been around Canvas for long
at all, you know that our lead pastor is covered in tattoos, and our associate pastor usually
wears shorts and a t-shirt.
So I put dress pants and a dress shirt on.
This is my Halloween costume.
I am a real pastor this morning.
So excited to be here to wrap up our series through the book of Daniel.
Today is going to be a little bit different than most of the sermons that we have at Canvas.
We are actually kind of summarizing the whole last half of the book of Daniel in one message,
because it's on the end times and prophecy.
And it worked out perfectly, because again, it's Halloween.
We're going to read about some beasts that have horns coming out of their heads.
One of the horns grows eyes and starts talking like a human.
It really is a perfect passage for Halloween.
But I'm excited and also a little bit anxious, because any time you start talking about end times
and eschatology, some people want to leave because they don't want to talk about it at all.
And other people are obsessed with it and have maps that they've hand-drawn of exactly what they think is going to happen
and how it's going to happen.
And we'll talk a little bit about both of those people more as we go on this morning.
But the message really is going to be a little bit different, because I really have two messages built into one.
One, the overarching message is I want to talk to us about how we should read prophecy.
Like, I want to give us an overview so that when we find ourselves reading prophetic passages on our own,
we kind of have an overview, an idea of how to read those things.
There's an application that's going to come with that.
And then inside of that overarching message, we're just going to walk through Daniel 7, which is a prophetic passage.
And I'm just going to show you as an example of how we would read that using that overarching message.
Does that make sense?
Hopefully.
All right.
That's kind of how we're going to go with it.
Just to review where we've been so that you know where we're at so far,
we've said throughout this series in Daniel that the Bible isn't just about what happens,
but it's about what always happens.
And what we mean by that is Daniel's a real character.
Babylon's a real place.
We believe these things happened, and they were recorded for us for a reason.
God preserved the story of Daniel for us for a reason.
He preserved the narrative section of Daniel to encourage our hearts,
to show us that believers who find themselves in secular nations,
nations that don't want to follow the things of God,
that we as believers, we can stay true and faithful to the things of God,
and we can have an impact in our world, in our culture,
even when our culture disagrees with our values.
So the book of Daniel was written to inspire hope in the hearts of believers in every generation.
But today, as we turn our eyes to the prophetic section of Daniel,
we believe that all prophecy in the Bible was written to give hope to hurting people.
Like whenever we see prophecy in Scripture,
it's always at a time when God's people are struggling,
when they're in bondage, when they're in slavery.
And God gives these prophetic visions of the future to remind His people
that He is sovereign and in control of all things.
And even if they can't see Him working out all things together for good,
they can hold fast and believe it in the midst of struggle,
they can know that ultimately one day God is going to come back
and He's going to right every wrong,
and He's going to bring peace and justice to the land.
And so when we look at prophetic Scriptures,
we should be getting hope, we should be inspired for the future,
even if we can't see it in the present.
A couple of disclaimers up front before we get into the specifics.
Prophecy often brings with it a discussion about eschatology.
Eschatology is a fancy word that theologians use to make themselves feel smart.
It just means end times.
And so everybody, there's multiple views on the end times,
and oftentimes some people are very passionate about their views of the end times.
And some people have no clue if they even have a view of the end times, right?
And so there's people all over the spectrum.
And I recently heard a pastor say that every view of eschatology comes with its assets and its liabilities.
Like there's no perfect framework.
There's no perfect structure that makes everything make sense perfectly.
And so we should hold those things loosely.
We should hold those things with an open hand.
Some of you in here, you might have a firm grasp on what you believe about the end times,
about how it's all going to work out.
Some of you might have no clue and maybe are kind of dreading the fact that you're even here this morning.
You're like, man, I came to the end times message.
Darn.
I find myself somewhere in the middle.
And so no matter what level of certainty or passion you have when it comes to eschatology,
let's make sure that our hope is firmly planted in the right place.
Let's be a people who are certain and passionate that Jesus will return.
And we hold up all of our other opinions in the open hand.
So that's kind of my disclaimer, where we're headed this morning.
Let me pray, and then we'll get into the specifics in Daniel chapter 7.
Father, we need you to be present and to be in this room teaching us your word.
Holy Spirit, I pray that each individual in this room would hear something from you this morning
that encourages them, that challenges them, that points them to the message of hope that we have in Jesus.
I pray that we would leave this place hearing from you and knowing what you would have for us,
knowing that we have a hope for the future.
God, conform us into your image.
It's in Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
If you have your Bibles, you want to turn to Daniel chapter 7, you can do so.
We'll get there in a little bit as I've been – this might be the longest intro that I ever do.
So if we get, like, halfway through the service and then we get into Daniel 7, I'm sorry, but we'll get there eventually.
So turn in your Bibles to Daniel chapter 7.
As you're turning, I'd like to ask you, how many of you in this room have known what this is or have ever used one of these?
We've got some hands.
This is a rangefinder.
Some of you might use rangefinders in hunting or golfing or maybe birdwatching.
If you guys are real intense birdwatchers, maybe you've used rangefinders in the past.
But rangefinders are cool.
It's kind of like a single-lens binocular, and you can look downrange, and you can see a very small field of view very clearly,
and everything else is kind of difficult to see.
And you can lock on to things, and it'll tell you how far certain things are away.
And most of my exposure – I have tried hunting recently, so this is actually a hunting rangefinder that I stole from a friend.
But most of my experience with rangefinders come on the golf course.
And I remember this time I was playing golf with a good friend of mine.
His name is Luke, and he's very good at golf.
I am very much not.
But what happens when you play golf with somebody who's very good at golf is they know just about exactly how far each of their clubs is going to hit the ball.
And so if they have a shot that's 150 yards, you pull the rangefinder out, shoot it, they know what club goes 150 yards.
They can adjust for the wind and the slope.
They do all these calculations in their head, and they can be pretty confident that once they hit the ball, it's going to go the distance that they want it to go.
And I was golfing with Luke one time, and he tossed the rangefinder to his buddy, Stephen.
He said, how far is the flag, or how far is the hole?
And Stephen shot down range and said, it's 160 yards.
So Luke said, okay, he knows how far his club that goes 160 yards goes.
He hits the ball.
It's flying right at the flag, perfect trajectory.
And all of us that aren't good at golf are watching the ball like, man, I wish my ball looked like that.
It never does.
And it landed in the sand trap behind the hole.
And Luke looked down at the ground, and he looked at his club, and he looked at his friend, Stephen, and he was like, did you say it was 160 yards?
And he's like, yeah, it's 160 yards.
Give me the rangefinder, because he knows.
He's a good golfer, right?
He knows.
I just hit that ball 160 yards.
And so he looks down the thing, and he said, you gave me the distance to the sand trap.
The hole's 150 yards.
The sand trap's 160 yards.
I hit it 160 yards.
And that's why I went into the sand trap.
And I think this perfectly illustrates for us our main point this morning about prophecy.
Because I think prophecy, as we look at Daniel chapter 7 and other prophetic passages of Scripture, oftentimes the writers of those prophecies, they're looking down rings through this small lens.
And they can see some things clearly.
They're getting imagery and pictures from God.
But they don't exactly always know when it's going to happen or how it's all going to unfold.
Sometimes they think they might be locking in on something, and they know, like, oh, this must be about to happen soon, and it's going to be in the future.
And so I think a rangefinder, as we look into this passage, is going to show us how we should read prophecy and ultimately illustrates for us my main point for this morning, and that is this.
We're going to keep coming back to this over and over and over again, that all prophecy points us to the first coming of Jesus or prepares us for his second coming.
When we look at prophecy in Scripture, all of it is either about the first coming of Jesus or the second coming of Jesus.
The whole point of prophecy is to point us to Jesus.
And we find hope and encouragement in that.
And so what we should do when we look at Scripture, Davis, you can throw that diagram up for me real quick.
What we should do when we look at prophecy is we should put ourselves in the position of the author, right?
And most authors of prophecy are on this side of the first coming of Jesus.
We've got creation.
We've got God's people in secular culture are all coming into the first coming of Jesus.
And Daniel is going to be somewhere over here on the left of this red X.
And what he's doing is he's looking down range.
And he's seeing visions and prophecies about the first coming of Jesus and about the second coming of Jesus.
And he doesn't really know exactly what he's seeing or what it all means.
But we have the privilege of hindsight, right?
Like we get to look back and try and work out some of this stuff when it comes to history.
So that's kind of what we're doing and how we should look at prophecy.
First Peter, chapter 1, says this about the prophets.
It says this salvation was something that the prophets wanted to know more about when they prophesied about the gracious salvation prepared for you.
So guys like Daniel were writing prophecy about Jesus, and they're asking God, like, what is this all about?
How is this all going to play out?
They wondered what time the salvation that the Spirit of Christ within them was talking about when he told them in advance about Christ's suffering and his great glory afterward.
They were told that their message was not for themselves but for you.
And now, this good news has been announced to you by those who preached in the power of the Holy Spirit who were sent from heaven.
It is all so wonderful that even the angels eagerly watched these things happen.
So we think about prophecy.
Prophecy either points us to the first coming of Jesus or prepares us for his second coming.
And God's working all of this out in some incredible ways.
So incredible and so amazing are the ways that God is working these things out, that the angels are in heaven watching it unfold, watching history unfold and unravel in such a way that the first coming of Jesus comes at the perfect time in the perfect way.
And they're like, wow, I never would have seen that.
I never would have designed something like that.
But our God is so good and so perfect.
And so they see the first coming of Jesus and now they're in heaven just anticipating how God's going to continue to unfold in human history to bring about the second coming of Jesus.
And so when we get into prophecy, I know it might be scary or difficult or seem overwhelming, but at the end of the day, all of it should give us hope because all of it is supposed to point us to the first coming or prepare us for the second coming.
Are we tracking so far?
All right, so that's kind of my overarching message that we're going to draw application from throughout the day.
But now that we have that framework, let's hop into Daniel chapter 7 and use that framework as we just use Daniel chapter 7 as an example.
And what I'm going to do here is walk through the traditional view of Daniel chapter 7.
There's other views of Daniel chapter 7, but I think the traditional view is best, and I think it works within this framework.
Because what we're going to see in Daniel chapter 7 is two things.
We're going to see a vision about four beasts with horns and all kinds of stuff.
It's going to be fun.
And I believe that those beasts are going to ultimately point us to the first coming of Jesus.
And then we're going to see a vision about the Antichrist and the Son of Man, and I believe that those things are about the second coming of Jesus, right?
So it's like this framework that all of these things are about Jesus, but sometimes we're looking downrange, right?
Like we're looking through this rangefinder, and it's not clear what things are going to come first and what things are going to come second and how it's going to all work out.
So my first overarching application for us as we think about prophecies, we think about the end times, and all of it pointing to Jesus is this,
that overconfidence in the specifics of our eschatology can easily knock us off in the end.
Like if you're one of those people that are fixated on the end times, that are fixated on the book of Revelation and prophecy,
and you read it all the time, and you've got those hand-drawn maps, and you think you know exactly when it's going to happen in exactly what order,
and you're trying to figure out which bowl of wrath is being opened up right now,
and if Vladimir Putin is the Antichrist and all of those things, I would just say that overconfidence in eschatology can easily knock us off our mission.
I don't know that Canvas is full of people with hand-drawn maps, but I'm sure there's some of us that tend to put our overconfidence in eschatology.
These people often have bunkers in their houses with, you know, enough canned food for like 10 years.
But we see this happen around the first coming of Jesus, right?
The Israelites were so confident in their view of eschatology, they thought the Messiah was going to come as a powerful political leader.
So when Jesus came as a suffering servant, they totally missed their promised Messiah because they had an overconfidence in their view of eschatology, right?
So like Jesus comes, and he rides on the back of a donkey into Jerusalem, and there's a crowd of Israelites, and they say,
Hosanna, which means Messiah, save now.
So they're getting it.
Like, they see that Jesus is this Messiah, this sent one of God.
But then he gets arrested by the Romans, and they're like, this can't be the Messiah because the Messiah is supposed to come as a powerful political leader.
He's supposed to overcome the Romans and set up his kingdom once and for all, forever.
They had this view of eschatology that didn't line up with the Jesus that they saw.
And so a week after saying Messiah, save, a week after claiming that Jesus was the Messiah, the same crowd yelled, crucify him, crucify him,
because they had an overconfidence in their eschatology.
And that overconfidence in their eschatology led them to miss the whole point of those prophetic passages, which was the first coming of Jesus.
So we can't be too overly confident in our eschatology.
We have to hold it with an open hand.
The thing that we're confident about is that Jesus is coming back.
All the other details we have to hold with an open hand.
Those of us that have overconfidence in eschatology, one of our favorite passages is found in Matthew chapter 24.
It says this, tell us, the disciples asked Jesus, tell us when all of these things will happen.
What sign will signal your return in the end of the world?
Jesus said, don't let anyone mislead you.
You will hear of wars and threats of wars, but don't panic.
Yes, these things must take place, but the end won't follow immediately.
Nation will go to war against nation and kingdom against kingdom.
There will be famines and earthquakes in many parts of the world.
But all of this is only the first of the birth plans with more to come.
And the good news, listen to this, the good news about the kingdom will be preached throughout the whole world
so that all of the nations will hear it and then the end will come.
So oftentimes people who have overconfidence in eschatology read rumors of wars and earthquakes and famine
and they're like, all that stuff's happening.
Jesus must be coming back soon.
And the reality is like all of that stuff has been happening ever since Jesus ascended into heaven.
Like wars, rumors of wars, earthquakes, bad things have been happening ever since Jesus ascended into heaven the first time.
But the one thing that Jesus tells his disciples to focus on before the second coming of Jesus
is to preach the kingdom into the whole world so that all the nations hear about me.
Our job is not to figure out exactly how and when Jesus will return.
Our job is to go into the whole world and preach the gospel of peace to the entire world until he comes.
We're here to welcome the strangers, care for the widows and the orphans, and preach the good news that sets the captive free.
Let's not let overconfidence or overfocus on the end times keep us from doing the most important ministry that Jesus has called us to.
So all prophecy points us to the first coming, prepares us for the second coming.
Let's just keep the main thing the main thing, not get overfocused on the details.
Now, let's hop into Daniel 7 and view this as an example.
Eighteen minutes in and we got to the passage.
That's a good sentence.
We're doing good.
So, Daniel says in chapter 7, he's earlier, during the first year of King Belshazzar's reign in Babylon,
Daniel had a dream and saw a vision as he lay in bed.
He wrote down the dream, and this is what he saw.
In my vision that night, I, Daniel, saw a great storm churning on the surface of a great sea with strong winds blowing from every direction.
Then four huge beasts came up out of the water, each different from the others.
The first beast was that like a lion with eagle's wings.
As I watched, its wings were pulled off, and it was left standing with its two hind feet off the ground like a human being,
and it was given a human mind.
Then I saw a second beast that looked like a bear, and it was rearing up on one side.
It had three ribs in its mouth between its teeth, and I heard a voice saying to it,
Get up, devour the flesh of many people.
Then the third of these strange beasts appeared, and it looked like a leopard, and it had four wings on its back and four heads.
Great authority was given to this beast.
And then in my vision that night, I saw a fourth beast, terrifying, dreadful, and very strong.
It devoured and crushed its victims with huge iron teeth and trampled the remains under its feet.
It was different from any of the other beasts, and it had ten horns.
As I looked at the horns, suddenly another small horn appeared among them.
Three of the first horns were torn out of the root to make room for it,
and this little horn had eyes like human eyes and a mouth that was boasting arrogantly.
I watched as the thrones were put into the place, and the ancient one sat down to judge his clothing as white as snow,
his hair like pure wool.
He sat on a flowery thorn with wheels of blazing fire, and a river of fire was pouring out.
Flowing from his presence, millions of angels ministered to him.
Many millions stood to attend to him.
The court began its session, and the books were opened.
Aren't you glad you came to church this morning?
So, later in Daniel, we're going to find out that these beasts were meant to represent kingdoms.
That's a clue that we have into how we can interpret the prophecy.
So, we have four beasts that ultimately represent four kingdoms.
And I believe the first kingdom represents the kingdom of Babylon, right?
It's like God has used the kingdom of Babylon to come in and to bring judgment to his people.
It says the beast was like a lion with wings.
And archaeologists have actually discovered that the national symbol for Babylon was a lion,
that there was lions all around the gates as you entered into the city of Babylon.
And so, this is not new to us, right?
Like animals representing political places.
It's like what represents America?
Eagle, right?
Like we're not shocked by some of these things.
So, we believe that the lion represents Babylon.
And then it says, look at this.
It says that his wings were plucked off, and then it was given a human mind.
That reminds us a lot of the story of Nebuchadnezzar, right?
Like it says that he went crazy, his hair grew out like feathers, and then his mind was restored to him.
So, we believe the traditional view points to the fact that this kingdom represents the kingdom of Babylon.
And this tells us that God is at work in secular nations to prepare for the first coming of Jesus, right?
Because the Israelites had disobeyed God.
We talked about this earlier in the series.
For 490 years, they just weren't letting the land rest.
They weren't doing what God told them to do.
And so, they owed God 70 years of judgment.
And God uses the nation of Babylon to bring about that judgment.
Ultimately, God uses Babylon to execute his judgment on the disobedient people of God.
So, kingdom number one, Babylon.
Then we move on to the second kingdom.
It says it's a bear that's stronger on one side and has three ribs in its mouth.
The Medes and the Persians come in, and they conquer Babylon.
And the reason that we think the bear is stronger on one side is because ultimately the Persians will overtake the Medes,
and the Persians will become the prevailing kingdom.
The Medes and the Persians, they conquer Babylon, and ultimately the Persians take over.
And listen, God uses the Medes and the Persians to end Israel's judgment.
It's the Medes and the Persians that send Israel back to Jerusalem to rebuild the wall and to rebuild the temple.
This had to happen for Jesus to come because Jesus would use the sacrificial system, the teaching of the law,
to illustrate that it's all a shadow of him who would come.
The atoning sacrifices made in the temple were just a picture of ultimately Jesus who would go to the cross
and be the sacrifice once and for all.
All of these things had to happen in order for the first coming of Jesus to come.
See, prophecy points us to the first coming or prepares us for the second coming.
So we've got Babylon and then the Medes and the Persians.
And the closer we get to the first coming of Jesus, I think the more prophecy comes out
and the more we see God actively working in secular kingdoms to prepare for the first coming of Jesus,
which I believe is the center of all human history.
That's why on that diagram there's a red X at the middle.
The first coming of Jesus is the center of human history.
And so the closer we get to that, the more prophecy is written and the more we can see God actively working in the secular kingdoms,
which brings us to the third kingdom, which we believe or the traditional view says is Greece.
It's a leopard.
What is a leopard known for out of all the things?
Speed, right?
A leopard is fast.
So we think it represents the kingdom of Greece because the kingdom of Greece conquered pretty much the known world in ten years.
Alexander the Great, like, just went on a spree and conquered everything around them.
The history actually tells us that after ten years he conquered everything and then he lamented because there was nothing left for him to conquer.
Like, his hobby was conquering other nations and then he conquered all the other nations and he was bored.
So we see that God is working through these secular kingdoms to prepare for the first coming of Jesus.
What does Greece bring us that might make it helpful for Jesus to come the first time?
It brings us a common language and a common education system.
Like, these would be important things for a message to be delivered to the known world,
that there would be one language that everyone would know and understand
and that there would be one worldview that they're all kind of coming from.
And so we see God actively working in secular kingdoms.
And as I was studying this week, I came across this incredible story.
That's not in Scripture, but it's from history.
And it shows us how God was just working and moving in secular history to prepare for the first coming of Jesus.
It's found in the writings of Josephus.
Any of you familiar with Josephus?
He's a Jewish historian that was kind of a contemporary of Jesus.
And he writes about the nation of Greece.
And he tells this story that's incredible.
It's so incredible that secular scholars, it makes secular scholars believe that Daniel was written after Jesus.
They're like, this story is so incredible.
There's no way it could have happened.
It had to be manufactured by the Jews to try and prove that the Bible is true.
So what happened is the Jews were operating the temple.
They were under the command of the Medes and Persians at the time.
And Alexander was starting his conquest.
He was starting to conquer all of these nations.
And he reached out to the high priest of the temple.
And he asked for rations.
He asked for help to feed his soldiers.
Right?
And they said no because they're being led by the Medes and the Persians.
They're kind of scared that they're going to get in trouble for, you know, feeding the army that's about to try and conquer the people that are in charge of them.
So the high priest was like, yeah, I can't do that.
I made promises to the Medes and Persians.
And that made Alexander pretty mad.
So he's like, all right, I'm going to go to these religious leaders and have a talk about why they won't feed my soldiers.
And as he's marching towards the temple to have a conversation with the high priest, he has a vision at night where he saw a man dressed in purple.
And that man told him to arise and defeat the Persians.
And as he marches closer and closer to Jerusalem, the day that he gets to Jerusalem, the high priest and the other priests decide to go out and meet him.
They're doing some damage control, right?
Like, let's go out and meet this guy.
And hopefully we can, like, reason with him.
Hopefully he understands why we're in the situation that we're in.
The high priest, or all of the priests dressed in white, and the high priest decides to put on purple.
This is what history tells us.
The high priest goes out to meet Alexander.
Alexander sees the high priest dressed in purple, and he says, you're the man.
That's all in the vision.
That vision told me that I was going to conquer the Medes and the Persians.
And the high priest starts to put all of these things together.
He marches Alexander into the temple, and he pulls out the book of Daniel.
And he reads this vision from Daniel chapter 7 about the leper that's going to overcome the Medes and the Persians.
And the high priest says, I think your vision was from our God.
I think he's saying it's your time.
And Alexander is so overcome that he actually makes a sacrifice to God in the temple.
And through these conversations, what the high priest asks is, hey, it looks like you're probably about to beat the Medes and the Persians.
Like, can you let us just keep sacrificing in our temple?
Just let us keep having the religious law that we have.
And we'll do whatever you ask us to do, but can we just keep having this temple open?
And Alexander makes this partnership with the high priest.
How incredible is this that we see God actively working through history to prepare for the first coming of Jesus?
The second application I want to draw out for us is that God is sovereignly working throughout all of us.
Of human history to accomplish his purposes in the perfect way and at the perfect time.
Like, the closer we get to Jesus, the more we see God working.
And we have hindsight, right?
Like, we can look back and see how cool it is that God's doing all of these things, bringing about a common language, bringing about a common education system.
We're going to see in Rome the greatest road system ever designed.
We're going to see Pax Romana, that there's peace across all of these different cultures.
It's a perfect storm for the message of Jesus to be delivered to the entire world.
God is sovereignly working throughout all of human history to accomplish his purposes in the perfect way and at the perfect time.
Because we need to allow this principle to affect the way that we view the events around us.
Like, the way that we see things happening and unfolding, we might be tempted to look at coronavirus.
We might be tempted to look at some of the politics and some of the wars that are happening around us and say,
How could God let this happen?
This doesn't seem good.
I don't see how this ends well.
And the same could be true of the nation of Israel, as all of these secular kingdoms were conquering and enslaving.
And they could have easily said, God, we're supposed to be your people.
You're supposed to protect us.
You're supposed to deliver us.
You're supposed to watch over us.
And yet we find ourselves in all of these difficult and negative situations.
And I think the same can be true of us today.
I don't know about you, but I can easily get discouraged by the current events of our day.
And we need to remember that our God is still on the throne.
That He's still sovereignly at work in our generation to accomplish His perfect purposes at the right time.
God's ways are higher than our ways.
His thoughts are higher than our thoughts.
And we might look at the current events around us and say,
If I was God, I would do things differently.
This is not who would be in charge.
This is not how things would work.
This is not the situation that I would design.
But ultimately, we have to believe and find hope in the fact that God is sovereign and in control
and that He knows better than we know.
And that He's ultimately working out this plan for His glory.
All prophecy either points us to the first coming of Jesus or prepares us for the second coming,
which leads us to the final kingdom we see in Daniel chapter 7.
The fourth beast, the fourth kingdom, we believe, represents the kingdom of Rome.
It gets us to the first coming of Jesus.
It was a terrifying and dreadful beast, different than all the others, with iron teeth.
Rome was a very different nation than all of the other nations that had come before it.
And it ruled with this incredible power where they used crucifixion as a tool to make all the other nations submit.
That Pax Romana we talked about, that peace among all of the nations connected to Rome,
that came through their strength, their brute force.
God used Rome to develop this peace among the known world and to bring about a road system,
like we said earlier, that was perfect for the proclamation of the good news of Jesus.
God will even make a secular nation pave roads, if it can be used,
if those roads can be used to deliver the message of hope to the poor, the powerless, and the persecuted.
God is sovereignly at work through these kingdoms, through these nations,
preparing for the first coming of Jesus.
So we see Jesus come right at the perfect time.
This gets us up to the death, burial, and resurrection of Jesus.
I think verse 9 and verse 10 shows us that Jesus conquering the enemy,
having the victory that he was sent to have.
Verse 9 and 10 says,
I watched as thrones were put in place, and the Ancient One sat down to judge.
His clothing was white as snow, his hair like pure wool.
He sat on a fiery throne with wheels of a blazing fire,
and a river of fire was pouring out, flowing from his presence.
Millions of angels ministered to him.
We have Jesus in the kingdom of Rome.
And the world might have thought that they had victory
when that cleansed Messiah hung on the cross.
But we know that he entered to the depths, he set the captives free,
that he rose again and ascended into heaven and seated at the right hand of the Father
until he comes again.
All prophecy points us to the first coming of Jesus who prepares us for his second coming,
which is where we get into some of the weird stuff here in Daniel.
You guys tracking with me?
I know this is a lot of content.
This is different than any message that we normally do.
So we get to Rome, which is a kingdom like different than any other,
and there's ten horns, and another little horn comes up,
and his eyes are like human eyes, and his mouth is boasting arrogantly.
That language, that verbiage is deceiving.
This is what we believe is the spirit of the Antichrist
that's going to be at work from every kingdom on.
From Rome until Jesus comes back,
we believe the spirit of the Antichrist is at work in every nation,
in every language, trying to deceive people,
trying to get them to live for less than God's design.
We know this from 1 John 2, verse 18.
John says,
My dear children, the end is near.
So all throughout the New Testament, they talk about the end times, right?
Like we're living in the last days.
So any time from the first coming of Jesus to the second coming of Jesus
are these last days.
And John says,
My dear children, the end is near.
You're living in the last days.
And you have heard that the enemy of Christ is coming.
The Antichrist is coming.
And now, many enemies of Christ are already here.
So we know the end is near.
So I think this horn that rises up and begins to boast arrogantly
to try and deceive is the spirit of the enemy at work
in different leaders, in different cultures
throughout all of human history from the first coming to the second coming.
There is a spirit at work behind secular culture
trying to get God's people to live for less than God's design.
We've talked about this all throughout the book of Daniel.
This is the third application I think we can draw out,
that the spirit of the Antichrist is at work in every generation
to get people to live for less than God's design.
And for whatever reason, I grew up thinking that the Antichrist was going to, like, be super clear.
He was just going to rise up and be like, I hate God in all things God.
And you guys should get a tattoo on your forehead
and declare that you also hate God, right?
But the enemy is a great deceiver.
He's at work in subtle lies.
Oftentimes, the spirit of the Antichrist is just trying to get us to believe small lies.
The same thing that Satan did to Adam and Eve, he's still doing to us.
The Antichrist is still trying to deceive us with misinformation.
He's trying to get us to doubt God's goodness in our life.
And we see this throughout cultures in our day today
that are promoting ideologies that promise the same type of peace and justice
among the land that God's kingdom does,
but they lack the ability to actually deliver it.
Like, there's ideologies today that are promising peace for the poor and the powerless,
that are promising that if you adapt our ideology,
that we're going to crush the power systems,
that we're going to raise up the people who are suffering,
and we're going to bring this peace and prosperity on the land,
and everyone's going to have a fair share,
and everything's going to be even and fair.
That sounds like the kingdom of God, right?
Like the kingdom of God brings peace and prosperity and justice to the land.
And there's ideologies that are promising this,
but the problem is they can't deliver
because these systems and ideologies are built on sinful people,
and sinful people are always going to do what sinful people do,
and that's sin.
There's always going to be these broken systems until Jesus returns.
So let's be on guard.
Let's pay attention to the ideologies that are being taught to us,
and let's continually go back to Scripture and refocus ourselves on Jesus.
But these prophecies get us to the first coming and then going out.
We see, as we wait and eagerly anticipate what I believe is the culmination of human history.
We see that the first coming is the center of all human history.
The second coming of Jesus is the culmination of all human history,
which gets us to verse 13.
Enter the Son of Man.
The Son of Man is Jesus' favorite terminology for himself.
It says this in verse 13.
He was given all authority, honor, and sovereignty over all the nations of the world,
so that people of every race and nation and language would obey him.
His rule was eternal.
He will never end.
His kingdom will never be destroyed.
This is Daniel's prophecy about the second coming of Jesus.
We believe that Jesus is going to come on the clouds and set up a kingdom that will last forever,
a kingdom that will never be destroyed.
Jesus' favorite term for himself was the Son of Man.
Right before he was crucified, the religious leaders were interrogating him.
They were trying to get him to confess to some things.
And they asked him, are you the Messiah?
Are you this promised Savior?
And Jesus said, I am.
And you will see, quoting Daniel, the Son of Man seated in the place of power at God's right hand,
coming on the clouds of heaven.
All prophecy points us to the first coming of Jesus or prepares us for his second coming.
See, Daniel 7 and all other prophetic writings, as we look into them,
just imagine that you're looking through this range finder down into the future
from where the author writes it to the second coming.
And some things are pointing to the first coming of Jesus.
Some things are pointing to the second coming of Jesus.
And some of the things are really weird and hard to understand, right?
I'm like, that's just, we got to be okay with that.
And just boil it all down to this, that all prophecy points us to the first coming of Jesus
or prepares us for his second coming.
My last application I want to draw out for us this morning is that prophecy about the end times
should inspire in our hearts hope, not fear.
I grew up in churches that would read Revelation and Daniel and Isaiah and try and use it to scare you,
try and use it to make you live in fear.
And the reality is prophecy about the end times, though sometimes sounds scary and weird and confusing,
it's all meant to remind us about how God was faithful to send Jesus the first time
and to encourage us to live with anticipation that he will send Jesus the second time.
Prophecy about the end times should inspire in our hearts hope and not fear.
I know earlier I was a little bit hard on those of you that like to spend a lot of time thinking about eschatology.
The reality is I think the opposite can be true, that sometimes we might ignore it,
not think about it enough or at all.
And the thing about that is in Scripture, scholars say that for every one time the Bible prophesies Jesus' first coming,
it prophesies about Jesus' second coming four times.
So there is this focus on the second coming of Jesus, that he will return, that he will right every wrong,
that he will make all things right.
See, when the early church believers would meet together after the first coming of Jesus,
they would shake hands, they would do this weird thing, they called it a holy kiss.
We don't do that anymore.
We didn't do it before Corona and we're not going to do it after.
They would greet each other with this holy kiss and they would look each other in the eye
and they would say, Maranatha, which means come Lord Jesus.
See, they were confident.
They knew that Jesus was going to return.
And that knowledge, that expectation inspired in their hearts hope.
Although I think we can get weird about the specifics of the end times,
church, it would not hurt us to talk about the coming of Jesus more often.
It would not hurt us to encourage one another daily to remind each other that Jesus is coming back.
So what does that do to our minds and our hearts?
Well, we started the message in 1 Peter chapter 1.
I think we could go back there for this end.
It says, the prophets were wondering what their message was about.
And they were told, this good news has been announced to you by those who preached in the power of the Holy Spirit sent from heaven.
It is also wonderful.
Even the angels are eagerly watching these things happen.
So what do we do?
The next verse, it says, so, think clearly and exercise self-control.
Look forward to the gracious salvation that will come to you when Jesus Christ is revealed to the world.
See, all prophecy points to the first coming of Jesus, prepares us for his second coming.
So, let us prepare our minds and set our hope on the expectation of the second coming of Jesus.
We have the privilege of looking back hindsight to 2020 and seeing how faithful God was leading up to the first coming of Jesus.
That he was sovereignly in control and working all things out in human history to bring about the first coming of Jesus.
And so we can be confident that even in the midst of these difficult circumstances, we find ourselves in.
We can be confident that he's sovereignly working and in control today.
We can be confident in the second coming of Jesus.
So, I can't think of any better way to wrap up a message about the first coming of Jesus and about the second coming of Jesus than to take communion together.
The reality is I grew up in a tradition.
I talk about my tradition a lot.
And a lot of times I talk about it negatively.
We got a lot of good things from our growing up and the people that we love.
But oftentimes when we did communion, again, it was used to make me feel guilty and bad.
It was all about the first coming of Jesus.
And we just focused on how brutal his death was.
And it was all our fault that his death was happening.
And that's all true.
All of that is true.
We're like, Jesus' body was broken and his blood was shed for you and for me because we sinned, because we fall short.
He had to do it.
He chose to do it for us.
But when he sets up communion, he says,
But I'm not going to eat of this bread or drink of this cup until I come again.
The reality is communion is just as much about the first coming as it is about the second coming.
We don't just take, when we take communion, we don't just look back at the blood that was spilled, but we look forward to the cup that will be raised.
Communion is a perfect illustration of this overarching message that all of prophecy either points us to the first coming of Jesus or prepares us for his second coming.
And communion is all about looking back and seeing that God is faithful to do what he promised to do.
And so we can be confident that he's going to be faithful to do what he has also promised to do, but yet to do, which is send Jesus again.
So in a minute, I'm going to lead us in communion.
Communion is for those of us that have placed their faith and trust in Jesus, that we believe in who Jesus is and what he did at his first coming.
And that he's coming back and that one day we will all sit around the table and share in this meal together when his kingdom is established that will last forever.
If you're in here and you're not sure where you stand with Jesus, then I hope that the way that you've seen God work through history in this message is enough to at least stir in your thoughts and questions about whether or not his claims could be true.
I'd encourage you to take this home with you and just think about the claims of Jesus.
See, often when people were considering whether or not they should follow Jesus, he gave them these really brash statements to make them think about what they were doing.
He would say things like, you've got to hate your mother and your father if you want to follow me.
He would say things like, you've got to eat my body and drink my blood.
So I think taking this cup home with you would be a great thing to put in front of you as you consider whether or not Jesus is worthy to be followed.
Because it's not this, just pray one prayer and never think about it again.
Following Jesus is embracing the sacrifice of Jesus.
It's placing your faith in his body broken for you, his blood shed for you.
So you said, take this home, think about it.
Reach out to us.
We'd love to help you walk through whether or not Jesus is worthy of following.
We'd love to answer any questions that you might have about that.
But for those of us who are followers of Jesus, I encourage us this morning to take communion together,
to remember not just the blood that was spilled, but the cup that will be raised.
Let's take the body of Christ broken for us.
Let's take the blood of Christ that was shed for us.
Let's pray.
Father, I pray this morning that we would find encouragement in the prophecy in Scripture,
that it ultimately points us to the message of Jesus, to the kingdom of God,
to the first coming of Jesus, and to the second coming of Jesus.
And we don't always see clearly how that's going to work out or what that's going to look like.
But you were faithful the first time.
And so we can trust you to be faithful the second time.
I pray this morning that each and every person in this room will find encouragement and hope,
knowing that you're going to return.
You're going to wipe away every tear from our eyes.
You're going to take away the weapons of war.
You're going to set up a kingdom of peace and justice among the land forever.
Nothing can take that away from us.
So in the meantime, God, we look towards you with hope.
And we live lives that proclaim the message of Jesus to the lost, the broken, the hurting, the poor, the powerless.
We preach that message until you come back.
God, encourage our hearts this morning to continue to live for you.
We love you so much.
We thank you for Jesus.
It's in his name we pray.
Church, thanks for hanging with me through a college lesson on end times.
I hope you guys have a great rest of your day.
We'll be right back.